Hello, welcome everyone. It is July
17th, 2025. We're in active imperence
guest stream 114.1
with several of the authors of how do
inner screens enable imaginative
experience? applying the free energy
principle directly to the study of
conscious experience.
Thank you to the authors who have joined
and to Coya for precipitating this
stream. So without further inner screen
stream ado, Chris, please however you'd
like to take it and I'll scroll to
wherever you need.
Okay. Uh thank you Daniel. Uh thank you
Adam and Maxwell for being here and
thanks to our other co-authors who uh
are not here for whatever reason. Uh one
of which is because we changed the
schedule on this presentation by an hour
uh at the very last moment.
Um so we just wanted to talk a little
bit about this paper and then open it up
to questions.
So it'll be it's good that that you have
some questions prepared.
So what's the basic motivation here? Uh
the basic motivation is simple. Uh if
one looks at any kind of standard active
inference picture of what's going on in
the middle of that picture is a Markoff
blanket and in fact we could look at
figure one and because that illustrates
this
and this is um all very familiar.
uh one has some system that's
interacting with some environment and
the interaction is mediated by a
boundary and the boundary is what keeps
the states of the system conditionally
independent from the states of the
environment. It's called a marov
blanket. Uh in the quantum formulation
of the FEP it's a holographic screen.
They have exactly the same function.
They encode information flowing from the
environment to the system. That's called
sensation.
And they encode information that's
flowing from the system to the
environment. That's called action. Uh,
of course, that's what it's called from
the systems point of view. Uh, from the
environment's point of view, the systems
actions are its sensations
and the environment's actions are the
systems sensations. So it's all a
completely symmetric system with this
markoff blanket boundary in between that
encodes the information exchange from
one to another.
So now in this standard picture if we
ask what can the system possibly be
conscious of
there's a fairly obvious answer. uh can
be conscious of its sensations and maybe
conscious of its actions cuz all that's
data that's written on its markoff
blanket.
Um and then in some vague sense maybe
it's conscious of something that's going
on inside it
and that's where the the problem is.
What does it mean to say that a system
is conscious of internal states or
internally generated experience?
And in the most straightforward reading
of the FEP,
uh that simply doesn't happen. All
that's going on internally is some
dynamical system doing its thing, some
bunch of physics, uh some vector
floating around in a state space. And we
can make this very precise in the
quantum formulation. And the quantum
formulation, what's going on inside the
system may just be unitary evolution of
some pure state in some almost isolated
Hilbert's face.
And so on the inside of the system, at
least on the quantum formulation,
it's very easy to stipulate that there's
no classical information at all.
Um nothing that could be experienced, no
definite states that aren't big
superpositions of all the possible
values of all the possible degrees of
freedom.
So at least in that way of thinking or
in that formulation if there are no
boundaries inside the system that
function is more of blankets
there's no possibility of inner
experience
and if there are boundaries in the
inside of the system that function as
markoff blankets then the experiences
encoded on those boundaries are the
experiences of the systems that are
bounded by those boundaries i.e parts of
the system not the whole system.
So in this way of thinking about the FEP
which which is again is kind of the most
straightforward possible way of thinking
about it
what a system experiences is only the
data that's written on its markoff
blanket either by its environment or by
itself.
So the motivating question for this
paper is how do we account for
imaginative experience in that kind of
model?
And the answer is pretty obvious. We've
got to invoke some sort of inner
boundary or inner marov blanket or inner
screen
um that mediates this experience.
and we've got to somehow see the agent
of interest as being inside that
boundary. So that's what we do in this
paper.
Um so if you Daniel would please fast
forward to figure three.
There it is. Uh I don't know whether
it's any it's it's possible to make that
a little bit bigger on the screen but
yeah that's better.
Um,
this is kind of a stripped down picture
of an active inference agent that's
complicated enough to have several
perception action loops, which we've
labeled QRF for quantum reference frame,
which is the representation of a
perception action loop in the quantum
formulation.
And what controls these uh perception
action loops specifically by allocating
attention to them. Um and we think of
attention in again the simplest possible
way as allocating energy to uh allow the
things to actually function.
Um what controls all that is some sort
of executive system which is a meta
controller or a meta processor in uh
kind of software language or software
architecture language.
And since these
perception action loops are exchanging
information with this metacontroller,
there must be a boundary inside.
And that boundary defines what the meta
controller experiences. What the
metacontroller experiences is the
activity state of the perception action
loops. That's what it's trying to
control. And it also experiences
whatever output they give it. So they
might identify some object and tell the
meta controller, oh that's a table or
that's a conspecific or that's a
predator or that says something else.
Um,
and the system as a whole experiences
what's written on its boundary which is
labeled B here by its environment.
Um, so we have two different kinds of
experience going on. Now we have an
experience on an outer screen which is
information encoded by the by the
environment or information encoded by
the systems actions and information on
this inner screen called BMC
which is just the experience of the meta
controller but it's also the experience
of the perception action loops
um that they get from the meta
controller. So they they can experience
the data that the meta controller writes
in their boundaries.
And these sort of black things that look
like valves at the top are meant to
indicate the flow of control i.e. the
flow of energy, resources, memory, uh
precision, whatever you want to call it.
um
from some resource pool uh to these
perception action loops or QRFs.
So this this simple architecture does
not encode or support any kind of
perceptual experience. So it doesn't in
support visual imagination or inner
speech or anything like that. Uh and we
can claim that based on
two or three decades now of cognitive
neuroscience
which indicate that imagination at least
in humans and presumably in in mammals
and and probably in vertebrates
uh employs the same kind of input
processing that perception does uh up to
a few details.
So when you have a some sort of
imaginative visual experience or or when
you engage in inner speech
um your fairly low-level perceptual
processes are engaged and this is fairly
well documented. So so imagination is
not just something that for example the
prefrontal cortex does or the executive
network does. It involves the sensory
systems.
So to make a model of imagination
uh in this active inference framework
uh that's realistic for the animals that
we know about we need to engage these
these perceptual modules.
So the solution to doing that um is
actually pretty straightforward. And if
you'll scroll down to figure four please
Daniel.
Um what we do is just add another
boundary
and this boundary is labeled BN in this
picture.
And we make the stipulation
that BN
uh can and typically does encode all of
the information that's on the the
boundary that's labeled here B out which
is the markoff blanket around the whole
system and that B in is what what the
system experiences
and this picture is complicated
by issues of control.
Not only does the the system the
executive system or the meta controller
need to manage the activity of the
perception action modules, these QRFs.
It needs to manage the flow of
information between be out the boundary
that the environment can write directly
on and be in.
And most of the time it's going to leave
those channels open,
but it needs to be able to close them.
For example, by closing the eyes or
stopping up the ears or something like
that. Um
and then
it can allow these perception action
modules to see information that either
themselves or other um
perception action modules have written
on this inner boundary.
So if you look at this picture uh and
think about popular architectures like
the global workspace
then clearly what we've done here is
just distribute the global workspace
between the metarocessor's boundary and
the inner screen boundary.
Um, and we've also indicated by the red
horizontal arrows here that sometimes
the meta controller may not actually be
possible to to completely suppress a
channel from the external environment.
So even when you're sleeping and
dreaming, for example, a loud enough
noise can typically wake you up.
And if you're driving on the highway and
sort of idally reminiscing about
something, uh events on the highway can
rapidly bring you to your senses, uh or
else you die.
So, uh there's heavy evolutionary
pressure to keep these channels openable
by the external environment.
And in mammals at least that's
implemented by the vententral attention
system which can override the dorsal
attention system and say no pay
attention no kidding that thing in front
of you is a tiger.
So that's what we've done in this paper
architecturally
is kind of followed u the standard
active inference architecture to one
logical conclusion
about uh experiencing content that's
created inside the system as if it was
content created outside the system.
And the remainder of the remainder of
the paper talks about what we know about
this capability, the capability of
imagination.
And
um the short answer is we know a lot
more about it than we did say 20 years
ago,
but we know a lot less about it than
we'd like to. So we know very little,
for example, about its phlogenetic
distribution.
We can look at lots of kinds of animals
uh including birds and octopi and
um certainly mammals
and infer that some of their behavior is
playing
and some of that play behavior at least
may be driven by internal imagination.
We don't know.
um
we can look at human variation
and see a lot of differences in human
capabilities to have imaginative
experience.
So for example, uh I'm pretty incapable
of having visual imaginative experience
aside from diagrams and so are a lot of
other people.
Um
we know that imaginative experiences
are involved in various ways in
pathology.
So uh for example
uh we know that one symptom of some
sorts of schizophrenia
involves uncontrolled imaginative
experience or failures of what's called
the reality monitoring system. confusion
between internally generated experience
and externally generated experience.
So a lot turns
on uh how imagination is implemented and
so it's important
uh for the active inference project to
have an implementation of act of
imaginative experience
that's fully consistent with all of the
other uh architectural
assumptions of of active inference.
So that's what we're trying to provide
here. And uh we've hopefully provided a
a very simple
um barebones kind of minimal assumption
model of uh what's required for this
kind of phenomenology.
And hopefully the model is is detailed
enough to be able to
provoke uh or at least encouraging
encourage
uh various further experimentation into
uh exactly how imaginative experience
works
in the at this point only system where
we really have uh access to reports of
imaginative experience even though they
may not be very reliable. and that is
us.
So, um that's kind of a summary of what
we're doing in this paper and I'm happy
to um answer questions or or if they're
not questions for for me, defer them to
my colleagues who know much more about
various aspects of this topic than I do.
Well, Chris, if I could just uh
if I could prompt you uh in a specific
direction, I think one one nice thing to
maybe discuss that was a great
presentation of the work by the way.
Thank you for being uh so, you know,
thorough and comprehensive. Um I was
wondering if you had a few words maybe
to add on the neocartesian angle. So I
think there's a sense in which the work
that we've done here kind of vindicates
something like a naturalization of the
homunculus. It certainly makes a lot of
these ideas a lot less um silly
sounding. Do do you do you have a view
there?
Well, I would say it uh
it it only vindicates in the same way
that the uh the global workspace model
does
the idea of an of an inner screen, an
inner um
locust, if you will, of classical
information in what could be an
otherwise quantum system or or an
otherwise boundaryless internal
boundaryless system.
It says that um to explain certain sorts
of phenomenology you need to have some
such construct
where where it differs from
the
classical homuncular picture which may
of course be a parody.
um is that
the systems
that it can experience what's on the
inner screen
are
in a in a very real sense smaller than
the entire system.
And one way in which they're smaller is
that there has to be stuff between the
inner screen and the outer screen.
And
that stuff
um
architecturally is not experiencable
by the system inside the inner screen in
this picture.
The other way that it differs is that
the executive system
and the executive system plus the
perception perception action loops have
very different experiences.
Um,
and
in a lot of kind of
I I'll call it folk psychology,
uh, the experiencing agent is more or
less equated
with its metacognitive system.
So
um
if I say
I'm currently experiencing X
that's by definition a report from my
metacognitive system
and because it has to be looking at
what's going on inside
um my cognitive system my total
cognitive system
and I think one implication of this kind
of work is that those reports are always
unreliable because the metacognitive
system is always working with a very
stripped down
uh coarse grained
abstracted
uh reportable experience.
So what I say I'm experiencing is is
actually not a very good guide to what
I'm actually experiencing.
And uh a corlary of that is what I can
remember experiencing is not a terribly
good guide to what I'm actually
experiencing.
So it it does make those challenges to
kind of folk psychological notions of
kind of inner life.
Yeah, thanks for that. Uh that that was
very interesting. Um, so I I know Adam,
yeah, you you unmuted. I was I was
hoping you also had something to add to
that. I know neocartisianism has been
one of the things that like I I think I
got the uh, you know, I was first
introduced to this idea by by you and
Sam Vasier about at the same time. So I
I hopefully uh this also sparks, you
know, interest, maybe even joy.
Interest, joy, and trepidation. Like I
guess I can blame you for partially like
not giving up on the idea cuz it's so
unpopular
cuz it's just like you know Dennett was
like so like clear and firm on this
point and so many people joined him on
like Daycart's errors and I mean clearly
there are problems there and I I I can't
deny what like you know with what Chris
is saying about like we can't just like
blindly trust like folk psychology or
our introspective access and we know
there has to be distortions. But I guess
one thing um I was wondering about is
whether some um quasi cartesian
intuitions
might actually reflect um both joints in
phenomenological space and potentially
guides to um how they're realized um
like in terms of what sorts of
implementations or computational objects
they might be. And so like this work
from Chris um you know it comes from a
very different background even though
like I'm also you know um inspired by
the the free energy principle. Chris is
coming from like um the fundamental
physics and like you know like how
quantum systems must um have like a
singular um interface or locality is
created in order to achieve I'm going to
butcher what I'm saying but like like
the way you're approaching this um is
very different for me but very
convergent and so then this idea of like
an inner screen um that's something I
was suggesting from my reading of um
both like um cognitive neuroscience like
neuro imaging literatures and also um
attempts at trying to make cross
mappings between um uh machine learning
architectures and um understandings of
neural function and and how they might
um you might interpret the brain as a
kind of um hybrid machine learning
architecture and generative model. But
would this um
so so in some of the work um uh some of
it explored with Tim Verb Balin um uh in
the context of robotics um uh the idea
is like interpreting the brain as a
cybernetic controller for an embodied
agent and
that's your slam paper with Tim right
yeah the slam paper
yeah cool very cool
what's cool is like in this work like
they have basically one of their core
data structures they use for robot
autonomy is a view in opposed network.
And so, you know, I I don't want to over
interpret or or overstress the
connection, but you know, I've um
sometimes somewhat fancifully, but
perhaps I should just commit to the
crime um thought of this almost like a
kind of quasi cartisian theater and
homunculus and their relation. And and
the idea is like you have the view of
the um of the robot and its pose as
being very two very closely entangled
data structures. are basically almost
the they're heavily mutually informing
each other because what you're seeing is
informed very heavily about where your
um sensors are pointed and um what and
that also what you're seeing gives you a
sense of what your body is doing. And so
these are these are the two primary data
structures and these are also if you
look at I guess like neural real estate
cortical hierarchies like the brain is
like dominated by like vision and then
touch and um so so an idea I I've been
exploring and it it wasn't I keep kind
of being um drawn back to it's not part
of the hardcore of any theory that if it
was falsified it wouldn't um like
disprove things the overall framework
but if it was like shown to be evidenced
I think it would provide Some support is
that potentially like um inner portions
of like um C the cortical hierarchy as a
kind of shared latent workspace could
potentially operate by principles of
geometric deep learning and potentially
correspond to something like a visual
spatial modality and a somatial modality
which are mutually um coupled and
informing. um something like a cartisian
theater and a homunculus but and and the
idea being that this being something
like um an inner screen and and and and
observer even though it's not really
strictly the sense that like you don't
have like homuncular regress and that
it's not like the um you have like um
the the clear problem of like aducing a
fully competent homunulous explanation
which requires a homunculus inside it.
that idea of something like a
centralized body like data structure in
relation to something like a centralized
visual spatial modality and that these
two mutually informing each other is
part of what brings coherence to the
sensorium. So in Chris's work here it's
like showing how like in coupling
quantum systems you need a kind of
singular interface to establish locality
and coherence. I'm I'm going to need you
to like like rescue me, Chris, cuz I'm I
shouldn't be speaking to I'm speaking on
the school, but I at least like
shamanistically,
I interpret this as a kind of
convergence of some quasi cartisian
intuitions. Now, how far you want to go
with them, I don't want to say like
we've like vindicated folk psychology
and like the points you made about like
you have to like, you know,
introspection has to get it wrong. Um
it's it's the whole point of you know,
you know, maps have to be simpler than
their territories. They have to diverge.
But I I do wonder whether like what
you've arrived at here could actually
provide some uh vindication for some
folk intuitions of a of a quasi
cartisian variety of the kind even that
um Dennit for all those years cautioned
us against. That's, you know, I I know
that's that's my personal inter um uh
one of the ways I'm uh thinking of this,
but you know, I I know it's like nothing
you're suggesting actually firmly
establishes that or depends on it or so.
That's my ramble. I don't know if that
made any sense.
I thought that was a great ramble. Thank
you, Max.
Yeah, I you know what what Dennett and
others uh fundamentally
cautioned against was kind of regressive
homuncularism where
every layer basically has the same
conceptual structure and every layer has
basically the same experience
and of course that won't do right.
Um,
so
I think what the
what the Marov blanket construction
I think forces us to do
is be
very careful
about saying
who has access to what information
uh within any
complicated layered hierarchical
uh multicomponent cognitive system.
And
um because it it
any such um
componentization
makes each of the components an agent.
And so each of the components has an
environment
that they exchange information with.
And so I think what the what the FEP
encourages is just being very careful
about that.
and um not assuming that a component has
access to information
that it can't get from some part of its
environment.
So if we think of u multiple components
interacting with a shared memory which
is basically what the G&W is
then
they have access to what whatever
information is written in the shared
memory
and that's not
kind of a difficult thing to think about
and that information may be fairly rich
But what it isn't is the same as the
total experience of any combination of
those systems.
Uh
each each system has its own experience
of whatever is written in that shared
memory.
And kind of the broadest
brush access to that information is is
more or less by definition what we call
the meta controller, the executive
system or something along those lines.
But again that's that's always coarse
grain. So I yeah I don't think the two
views are inconsistent.
I think um the the the
active inference picture of things
is is just a way of being precise about
it.
Thanks. Um COA, do you want to ask one
of your questions?
Sweet. Yeah, I was um
I was thinking about if the
uh metacognitive system is like a place
to gather the memories or um um yeah
it's it's like the the reason why we
have shared memories in the first place
is that that way around like locus to
which the memories of the other systems
can be shared too or something like that
but yeah that's uh speculative. So, um I
was thinking like one thing we didn't
talk about at all was this like the
quantum reference frames um
what to understand under this we skipped
like the figure and um where they end um
is like the coarse grained um structure
on the retina or something like this. Is
this part of quer reference frames or
are they starting
uh later in the hierarchy um with
concepts like um gestal or something
like that? Um
yeah, so that would be one question. Um
how deep the quantum reference frames we
are looking here in the inner screen. Um
are
I just lost your audio?
Oh, I just lost you.
Oh
you or is it
Yeah.
Yeah. Just repeat the question.
Yeah. So, um, we didn't look at the
quantum reference frames. Can you hear
me Chris?
Yes.
Yeah. Okay. So, we didn't talk about the
quant reference frames. And so one
question would be what are they in a
short um answer and then another
question uh related to this is um how
deep in the neuronal um architecture are
we talking about here? So um are we
talking about like something like pixels
or um single um uh um receptors in the
retina or are we talking about gestal uh
um representations
further down in the hierarchy? Um so how
um
yeah so how how deep does this kind of
reference frames that are um in the
inner screen?
Okay. Well um yeah thank you. Uh I can
answer both of those at least to some
extent.
So this construct of a of a quantum
reference frame that we use um
is is actually a very old idea
that's been formally
updated
in the last
two or three decades. uh really under
pressure from the uh quantum
communication and quantum security
communities.
So in classical physics you have things
called reference frames. Um for example
cartisian coordinates are a reference
frame
and
um
these are things that we use. So,
clocks, uh, meter sticks, all of those
are reference frames. What does that
mean?
Well, it means two things.
Um, a reference frame is both a
standard.
So, it defines a kind of unit, for
example, the meter,
and um, it's a way of measuring.
So, uh, a meter stick lets you measure
things in meters.
So, it it's those two concepts kind of
bundled together.
And in classical physics, these things
are treated as abstractions.
Uh, if you read Einstein's work, for
example, he's constantly talking about
moving frames of reference, etc., and
observers sitting on moving frames of
reference and reporting what they see
and on and on and on.
So as
quantum information started to become a
discipline, it was recognized early on
that this purely abstract way of
thinking of reference things frames
wouldn't do
that the physicality of reference frames
actually had to be taken into account.
So a meter stick uh is not an
abstraction. It's it's an actual object,
you know, it's a it's a piece of wood or
a piece of metal
that we hold in our hands
and we use it to interact with the world
and those interactions are actually
forceful and they require energy and so
on.
So measurement uh is not this completely
passive abstract thing where by magic
you get some information.
Uh you have to actually kind of whack
the world with something with your meter
stick to get some information out of it.
And that's the fundamental reason for
things like Heisenberg's uncertainty
principle.
So if you think about reference frames
in this physical way and then you think
about observers as physical systems like
us
and you ask so what's required for me to
be able to use a meter stick.
Uh I used to have one around here but I
don't see it right now.
Um so if I have this object a meter
stick and I want to measure length then
I have to have some concept of what
length is
and that concept has to be encoded in my
brain.
It has to be part of me as a as a
physical device.
And if I use a clock I have to have some
sense of time. I have to be able to
notice that the hands on the clock have
moved for example.
So I have to have a clock in my head. Uh
I have to actually be a clock in order
to use a clock somewhere out in the
external world. Otherwise I won't even
notice that the clock is moving.
So uh that led us to think about what
does it mean to say that the observer
implements
uh quantum reference frames that
components of the observer actually are
quantum reference frames and we know
from neuroscience for example that the
hippocampus encodes a very sophisticated
3D reference frame.
uh and we know that some of the
perihocal areas encode fairly fairly
sophisticated clocks. So we're not
making this up. It has some connection
to neuroscience. It's not completely
theoretically motivated.
So now we can ask
um what how do we want to conceptualize
these things?
And again, we think of meter sticks and
clocks as just objects in the
environment.
And they may do something like clocks.
Uh they may have to use energy and they
may just sit there like meter sticks.
Uh and they may be u outcomes of some
complicated physical process. So for
example, if I want to define what up
means if I'm measuring spin,
I'm generally going to do it with
reference to the Earth's gravitational
field. Well, what's that? Right? It has
something to do with the curvature of
local spacetime.
Then it defines an external reference
frame that I can use. I can use the
gravitational field or the magnetic
field to think about what up means.
But that requires that I have some
representation
uh that I implement some representation
that lets me access by interaction that
external
uh direction directionality either
magnetic
or gravitational. And we know that we
use gravity all the time to move around.
That's one of the key features of our
bodily system. And we know that birds
for example use magnetism uh in migr
migrating and that kind of thing. So
again this this is stuff that we know
about from a neuroscience perspective
also.
So uh to sort of come to a close on the
first question um a quantum reference
frame in this way of thinking is a
component
of the internal process of some
observer. And you can think of it as a
component of the internal process of
some organism.
And theoretically that internal process
is just some dynamical system or can be
represented by some Hamiltonian operator
or something simple. And of course we
have no clue about how to write those
operators down. Uh but formally they're
easy to play with. So you can think of a
quantum reference frame as just some
components of a dynamical system or a
Hamiltonian.
So now to the question of of how deep
are they?
And that's a subtle question
because one can construct
an arbitrarily deep hierarchy of
operators
and if those operators all have a
property.
So in quantum theory for example all
measurement operators are hermission
which just means that their igen values
are real. The outputs that they give you
are real numbers. And so you can since
they're finite resolution, you can think
of the outputs as as binary numbers,
some bit strings.
You can construct an arbitrarily large
hierarchy of these operators and the
whole hierarchy will be herian. So it
will look at the world and give you a
real bit string
provided one condition is met. And the
condition that has to be met is the
operators have to commute.
That's what those arrows mean in this
diagram that's on the screen.
And in quantum phys in classical physics
of course all operators commute
but in quantum theory they don't. So
quantum theory has the great advantage
of giving us a formalism that
automatically
lets us talk about failures of
commutativity. Which means that if I do
operation A and then B, I get a
different answer than if I do B and then
A.
And clearly a lot of our interaction
with the world has that
structure. If I do one thing and then
another thing, uh the second thing often
depends on the result of the first and
it can depend causally or it can depend
non-causally and if it depends
non-causally then that's quantum
non-commutativity.
Both kinds occur all the time.
So one advantage of the quantum
formalism is that it allows you to deal
with
non-commutabivivity
between operators which translates as
the inability to define joint
probability distributions over sets of
variables.
But if you can define a joint
probability distribution over a set of
variables however large it is uh you can
define one QRF over it.
And so you can think of
um things that for example in the dorsal
early dorsal visual system
uh identify moving edges. Okay, that's a
reference frame that identifies moving
moving edges. You can identify lots of
those in the visual field. Or you can
think of something that identifies
chairs. Or you can think of something
that identifies scenes.
Or you can think of something that
identifies short histories of different
scenes.
And as long as those the operators that
build up those identifiers commute, you
can think of that as one quantum
reference frame.
So you automatically get a a very deeply
hierarchical system that nonetheless
divides
splits into fragments. When you have
operators operations that don't commute,
when looking at the world changes it.
Yeah. Um
you want to respond or or ask anything
else for you, please?
Yeah. Thanks for the uh answer. Really
interesting. Um,
uh, I was thinking about what to do with
Adam's, um, questions or remarks. Um,
should I
address them now or later?
Sure. Um, you want to talk about it,
your thoughts.
Should who address what?
Uh Adam uh wrote like
I know four messages.
Yeah, Adam, if you write something in
the chat, please say it on the street.
Okay. Um so um
so Chris and your um work in like terms
of quantum interpretations of the FEP.
Um so you know so some people might you
know pattern match and then say like oh
uh you mean like orchestrated reduction
and like quantum computation but no it's
like a quantum formalism for um the use
of quantum formalism and um it it makes
me wonder like I you know I reached the
limits of my technical depth here but in
terms of like how far we can go with
like which um uh uh you know uh quantum
intuitions and interpretations. So like
um so for instance like when you're
thinking of like interacting neuronal
populations as they're coming like in
and out of coherence and they have like
probabilistic properties to like where
they're at in terms of their degree of
coherence as they form they couple
various types of synchrony these like
interacting like clouds of neurons. Um
is there a sense in which like um part
of the reason you could get um uh
quantum formalism from a neuronal system
is because of its like probabilistic
nature like some sort of mapping between
like basian brain-like ideas and like
the born rule of total probability or I
I guess um
that so then um but one of the things I
was wondering is like so if there is
this requirement for um in order to get
coherence about multip multiple
observers with a multiple reference
frames that that you get this like
establishment of a singular um interface
across them with like um locality and um
also coherent temporality uh but
locality at least as I understand it. Um
could this for instance like um so is
this like requirement maybe something
that's also sculpted by natural
selection or or development to some
degree like genetics helps it along but
like could this be part of what could
this get as a precision coherence as
like normal populations find ways of and
they interact in different ways to
achieve coherence that they establish
the the estab um the creation of a um
inner screen with locality as part of
this requirement for coherent coupling
and and so it's like um so again a
ramble but um uh so so the maybe the
better thinking of about quantum
derivation of inner screens it makes me
wonder about quantum formalism as a
source of mathematical interpretations
functioning seef basian brains and born
world tool probability whether
interactive neural populations as fuzzy
blanket probabistic sets each with their
own reference frame induce the formation
of semi-entralized inner screens as a
couple due the requirement of its
creation for coherent in coupling with
its locality and temporality
informationational properties and as a
source of and this also providing a
source of phenomenal coherence/binding
and as a source of something like a
quasi cartisian inner theater and
perhaps even a basis for um egocentric
projective geometric visual spatial
awareness and sensation/ imagination.
So, that's a lot of different things,
but I was just I'm wondering like um you
know, I'm at the limits of my technical
depth here of like where I should and
shouldn't go with drawing from um uh um
ideas from quantum physics and whether
what I said is somewhat in the ballpark
of like mappings between neuronal
functioning and quantum formalism.
Yeah, I I think this is very much worth
pursuing.
Um
I I wouldn't be surprised
if uh
neuronal coherence is not constantly
essentially drawing different boundaries
in the nervous system
across which classical information is
forced to flow.
Um, one reason for thinking that is that
phase coherence is so important
and phase coherence is I mean quantum
coherence is a measure of a particular
kind of unobservable phase coherence
and phase coherence is something that we
can't observe locally right we as as
outside observers can't observe phase
coherence locally unless we just happen
to look at the right two neurons or the
right two parts of some assemblage,
right? We won't notice that this one
over here happens to be phase coherent
with that one over there unless we're
looking correctly. And that's kind of
what unobservability means.
Um
there's reasonably good
experimental evidence
that human cognition exhibits intrinsic
contextual or non-causal contextuality.
Uh the relevant work was done by um
Edabar Zafurov and and Andre Krennikov
and their collaborators.
It's very careful experimental work and
and they understand the mathematics
intimately well.
Uh
so
from that perspective I mean Krennikov
insists on call it calling it quantum
like
but I think if
if it can only be described correctly
using the quantum formalism you might as
well just call it a quantum phenomenon.
uh because quantum theory doesn't have
any intrinsic scaling or anything like
that. I mean we associate it with the
microscopic for historical reasons but
black holes are quantum objects which
are some of the biggest things we know
anything about.
Um
so I think I think there's a lot to be
done there. I I think um probably the
formalism that that quantum theory
provides will actually make it much
simpler to think about neural behavior.
Uh because it does build in these kinds
of phenomena like phase coherence
that we know experimentally are
important.
But um we we lose our ability to think
about when we just think about things
like firing rate.
That was super interesting. I I'm going
to have to uh drop unfortunately I had a
hard stop now. Um but I think Carl just
joined us. Is that the case?
Yes. Yes. I've just
Excellent. So, it's like a relay race.
It's good to good to hear from you,
Carl. Um, so, uh, have a good rest of
the conversation, everyone. Thank you
very much.
Thank you, Maxwell.
All right. Thanks, Maxwell.
Good to see you all.
Yeah, I I'm going to have to depart uh
fairly soon, but I can I can at least
briefly bridge to uh to Carl's part of
the conversation if
Yeah.
Uh you you all want to carry on.
Uh what's what's happened so far, Carl,
is is just a brief description of what
the paper is about
and um followed by a um
some conversation about what quantum
reference frames are, what inner screens
are, and we're just getting to uh thanks
to Adam um a discussion of how
uh coherent activity among
distributed uh neurons
um may draw different uh effective
um boundaries and hence create construct
different effective markoff blankets
within the system.
So, you know, you know far more about
this than I do.
Mhm.
I suspect not, but thank you for
orientating me.
Maybe to to connect with the earlier
discussion and and uh continue on. Carl,
how would you see this in light of the
theater discussion and responses?
What
unique explanations and predictions come
from bringing this work together that
were absent packets and parcel and other
work that had active inference
perspectives on awareness and
consciousness but not the quantum.
Do you want to just unpack the theta
issue?
It it it came up a little bit, but
please, however you want to summarize
and continue.
Well, no, for my benefit, just to sort
of focus me, what what specifically were
you referring to when talking about
theater?
Uh, like your paper response to the
theater critics.
Oh, the theater. Sorry, I thought you
meant theater rhythms.
Oh, yes.
Right. It was in a different world. My
apologies. Let me let me orientate. Uh
and my response to the theater theater
critics. Right. That was a long That was
with Alan Hobson. Yeah. So that was that
was some time ago.
2016,
right? Yeah. Well, that's nearly 10
years ago. Can you can you remind me
what what you took from that paper?
Um
I'll just summarize from the abstract.
You wrote in brief. We fully concur with
the theater-f free formulation offered
by Adele and Doohurst and take the
opportunity to explain why and how we
use the cartisian theater metaphor. We
do this by drawing an analogy between
consciousness and evolution. The analogy
is used to emphasize the circular
causality inherent in the free energy
principle aka active inference earlier
times.
We conclude with a comment on the
special forms of active inference that
may be associated with self-awareness
and how they may be especially informed
by dream states.
And it was in that sort of era with the
I think therefore I am and the early
sorts of recursive basian models that
you were proposing and working on.
So how do you feel like this
paper extends and continues in that
line?
What do we gain in terms of explanation
and prediction from bringing in the
quantum formalism?
I can only answer that really from a
classical perspective. Um but I think a
lot has been um added to the stories and
a lot of nuance has has crept into it um
which is nicely framed by the uh quantum
information thetic uh formalism.
I um I'm trying to cast my mind back a
decade um and what was around then and
what uh what is around now. And um
certainly there's a lot more literature
addressing consciousness uh in its
various guises. Um and in particular my
mind goes to um a direct
confrontation of issues of experience
and um phenomenology.
Um and within that space the role of um
hierarchies and specifically the role of
um markoff blankets in defining those
kinds of hierarchies which begs the
question if there are hierarchies in the
brain.
First of all, is there an irreducible
blank um uh markoff blanket in the sense
that there can be no further um sparsity
of coupling or conditional independences
uh or dynamical architectures that admit
any further markoff blankets. So um this
was um one of the um
contributions from the classical
perspective uh to an early formulation
of the paper that Chris has just um
taken us through. Um the other thing
that's brought to the table is um if
there are markoff blankets within a
brain um what constitutes the active
states of any of these internal markoff
blankets. So that becomes an interesting
focus and the story um that people like
L. Sanit Smith and and the company
including people like Mark SS would
pursue is that the way that you act upon
things um lower in say a centrial or
centrifugal um hierarchy
would be primarily through mechanisms
like attention. But um your again in the
classical context would be read as
optimizing the precision or the
confidence ascribed to various
representations at lower levels. Um and
that's I think an interesting move
because that
weds the psychological interpretation of
that gain control active gain control to
attention in the psychology literature.
Um it also provides a nice link to um
Mark SS's notion of felt uncertainty
remembering that precision is the
complement or the inverse of uncertainty
and that there are people who would
regard any um feelings or qualitative
experiences um would require there be
there to be um a mechanism in the brain
that would um
render what was transparent opaque. That
would be attention or would from the
point of view of simulations um be the
uh the gain control that comes along
with this kind of mental action. And I
use the word mental action as another
way of describing the role of or the
process that would be implicit in having
active states on markoff blank blankets
in in the brain. So we're talking about
a a covert kind of action. Um and that
covert action can be read as attention
or it can be read as sort of uh um
actively um selecting those sources of
evidence for belief updating um within
on the internal side of the Markoff
blanket. So I think that's quite a nice
story um that sort of is quite
accommodating of a number of different
perspectives and different kinds of
formulation. Um but let's come back to
this notion of um an irreducible
um markoff blanket. I think that that in
itself is an interesting concept. Um,
and in many senses when I read Chris
talking about the inner screen, um, one
could argue, and indeed a lot of people
do argue, um, Shamil being, uh, one of
these people, Reuben, um, along with
Shamil being one of these people, that
there are, you know, there are a whole
host of inner screens. Um and I think
the most recent analogy is that of these
um smart glasses that through mental
action you can render opaque or
transparent with screen after screen
after screen. Um
so what is the inner screen? Um, and to
my mind, just in a very simple-minded
way, that has to be um the innermost
screen that surrounds a um the
irreducible Markoff blanket. Um, and
there's some interesting issues that
attend that. Well, if this irreducible
markoff blanket is responsible for
providing
um messages and if we take the quantum
theoretic formulation um then we're
talking about the holographic screen
that
um is surrounding the irreducible bulk
that constitutes this irreducible part
of the um of the system. Um, and writing
that classical information to the active
sector of the holographic screen has to
have consequences. And what are those
consequences? Well, we've just said, um,
from a sort of neurohysiological point
of view, it has to engage those
mechanisms that mediate gain control.
And immediately you're now drawn to
thinking, okay, well that basically
means that the projections of the inner
screen um must in some way do some kind
of attentional selection beyond the
screen and that's the sort of mental
action uh that that that um I was
referring to previously. Um so I think
the notion of the inner screen is
something which we didn't have until a
few years ago. Um and it if if you like
to my mind is is a denument of um
arguments that have been formalized and
developed over over the past 10 10
years. I'm not sure that speaks to the
the inner the um the theater debates. uh
they were more predicated on um if I
remember correctly a sort of dual aspect
monism that inherits from the um the two
kinds of information geometries that you
get from a classical physics perspective
where you're linking um the movement on
a statistical manifold to an information
geometry
which um essentially encapsulates a
belief space. So literally changing your
mind um to exactly the same or
supervening on on the same substrate
which would be a neurodal substrate that
you could cast in terms of neural firing
that has itself an information geometry
read as uh classical stochastic
thermodynamics. So where whenever
there's a a you know space of
probability distributions say of the
kind that underwrites
stat statist statistical or um
stochastic thermodynamics there is a
thermodynamics. So there's a natural
link there between the sort of the
energetics of the brain and the um
informationational uh or
representational uh geometry on two
statistical manifolds that superven on
on the same um on the on the same
substrate. How that perhaps I should
pass back to Chris now who hasn't gone
away so he's still here. Um so Chris
would wrap up that thermodynamic aspect
um into um a free energy se
thermodynamic free energy sector on the
holographic screen. Um so you know I
think there's an an interesting
discussion here um as to whether there
is a dual aspect well whether there are
any information geometries in the spirit
of um
the uh statistical manifolds and if
there are how are the thermodynamic
versus the um the classical information
structures linked
and I'll have a rest now was Not good
enough.
Thank you very much. Great.
Um, wow. Uh, I want to uh change
directions uh away from the theater to
something else. Um we've in the paper um
um yeah you talked about the phog
journey of imagination and um you gave
some reasons why um the second layer in
a screen um was implemented um and there
was the advant of cover action social
situations um could be better managed if
um some
um actions are covert and the other
thing was the planning in depth. Um I
was thinking maybe um um there's this um
senetic concept of second order
observation to use um the inner
observation on something else to see
what one person is using to experience
this thing. So to um reflect on the own
source and I think um this idea of this
inner screen uh could
um yeah really good at um capturing this
idea. So we we can use on the inner
screen a quantum reference frame to look
at another quantum reference frame and
to look what quantum reference frame we
used there. No like um a second odd
observation. And this could be maybe
like another um
um advent for this kind of architecture.
or is the um
could this be achieved with a um without
this inner screen?
Yeah, I
I think a very good question is
how does the system
represent its own capabilities?
Mhm.
Um, so in the kind of simple-minded
picture that we drew,
the
metacognitive system or the the
controller, the attention system
has to know something about what the
various perceptual and action
capabilities of the organism are good
for.
so that it can decide what to spend
energy on, what to spend energy doing.
And this we know that this goes way way
down in fogyny.
So, uh, we know that even bacteria
have very sophisticated
ways of,
um,
for example, swapping in or out whole
metabolic pathways
to deal with different food sources that
are present in the environment. And uh a
key discovery from the 60s and early 70s
was how this works. How the food source
itself
um is perceived and how the perception
of a food source can trigger
uh the expression of whole families of
genes that then encode enzymes
for metabolizing and using that food
source.
So you can think of that in terms of
meta control and you can think of that
as a system saying, "Oh, here's
something in the environment that tells
me that I should turn off a whole bunch
of my information processing and turn on
a whole other bunch of my information
processing. So in a sense, I should
switch what I'm paying attention to
and switch what I'm doing about it.
uh I should turn on whole different
perception and action capabilities as
units.
So we know that that that kind of
capability is is extremely deep in
fogyny. All all organisms have that kind
of capability.
So when we get up to these very complex
organisms that actually have brains,
[Music]
uh we can ask what's the analog of that
at the level of
um for example neural representations
in the motor system of what the arms or
hands can do.
uh and how those representations are
engaged
when you're faced with a problem like
picking up a coffee cup or you know
getting a nail out of a board with a
hammer.
um
your system and this is not consciously
very accessible information of course
kind of knows how to use the
capabilities of the limbs to do these
jobs
and uh so I think a question for
uh the discussion that uh Carl was just
annunciating
about attentional control
and metacognitive representation
is this question of how the system
represents its own capabilities from how
to use its limbs to
um you know how to mana manage its
immune system sorts of things that Mark
Solom is very engaged with to
much more abstract things like um
you Do I have the cognitive wherewithal
to read this paper and understand it? Uh
we do have some sort of understanding of
that that's difficult to articulate.
So I I think I think all of those
questions are aspects of exactly the
same kind of question of internal
resource representation or internal
capability representation
which an attention system has to have.
if it's if it's going to function in a
to do the the job that an attention
system has to do.
So, I'm I'm afraid I'm going to have to
depart too now. Um, but please carry on
as long as you like and uh thankfully
this is being recorded so I can see at
some later time what was said in this
latter part. So, thank you Carl for
joining and uh thank you all for for
being here and and being interested.
Thank you, Chris.
Okay. Does anyone have a comment or
question or I can read uh some of the
questions in the live chat.
Yes, Carl. Well, just picking up on on
that last question which I thought was
extremely interesting. I notice you put
the um strange things paper up on the on
the chat and I think that was that was
quite astute of you because um the very
notion of an inner screen tells you
immediately that anything lying behind
that inner screen does not have direct
access to the actuators to the active
states of any cell or any person or
indeed any population. And that has
quite a fundamental implication because
if you can always read the internal
states within a Markoff blanket
as or at least describe them as making
inferences about the cause of their
sensory sector. What that means is that
the internal states behind the inner
screen will also be representing in some
sense in some minimal sense their own
actions because the actions are going to
be vicariously a cause of the sensory um
the sensory impressions
or the sensory sector of the markoff
blanket. That's quite remarkable because
what that basically means is that if you
have an inner screen,
you effectively are inferring what
you're doing. You have basian beliefs
about your own behavior. You're not
directly aware of in the sense that
there's a dynamical coupling between
your active states. Uh say for example
the um the primary aference going to
your spinal cord. of the spinal cord
knows exactly the consequences of its
action, but the central nervous system
or parts of it behind the inner screen
do not. So you've now got this
interesting situation where you've got
beliefs, posterior beliefs or you can be
described as having as if you had
posterior beliefs about your own action.
Now if you've got posterior beliefs, you
must have prior beliefs.
If you've got prior beliefs about your
own action before it's happened, you
have intentions.
So, at some level, there's a bright line
between things that do and do not have
intentions. Um, and I would, you know,
just coming back to Chris's examples of,
um, um, you
the base of pheroggetic trees, perhaps
it'd be even simp.
Yeah, a thermostat has direct access to
the consequences of its action where
whereas I do not. So you could argue is
there a different kind of intentionality
or do does a thermostat have intentions
um in the same spirit that I have
intentions? And if your answer is yes,
then largely you are um answering or you
are making that discrimination or
disambiguation between things that are
and are not intentional on the basis of
possessing uh possessing an inner
screen. And then you can have a further
argument which I suspect um um um was
was um hinting at is um if I'm inferring
what I'm going to do or or to use
Chris's words, what am I doing? Then the
question is at what temporal scale is
the doing expressed? Am I leading a good
life? Am I going to the shops? Am I
adjusting my posture to increase my
comfort?
Am I reflexively um responding to heart
rate variability? All of these are very
different time time constants. So I
think there is a question now of the
temporal depth of the imagination. That
would be effectively a description of
the belief updating
to evaluate to infer
what you are um what your intentions are
or to form um um a poster belief that
will then be enacted by your reflexes um
that is predicated on your prior beliefs
about your uh about your action namely
your intentions. So I think there's you
possibly a vague um spectrum of things
that just look very myopically into the
future, say viruses
and things that look quite a long way
into the future, you know, things things
like you and me. So I think there's some
really interesting um like purely
technical um things that attend any
belief updating or any system that is
equipped with an inner screen that can
then be described as if it is doing a
certain kind of belief updating. And to
finish um the the the recursion and the
metacognitive aspect
um inherits from the fact that you don't
have direct access to the consequences
of your actions.
I'll ask a few related questions here in
the chat. So, Andreas asks, "Can we
introspect our Marov blankets or not?
What is being observed?
Who or what is there to observe that?
Are you going to answer that Daniel or
I think uh Chris would be um the prime
person to
answer those questions. Um
I'm not sure in this version of the
paper when there is a um
Daniel can you just scroll down just to
make sure there's not a a a figure. Ah
right perhaps that was that that was it.
I I I think there's quite a
straightforward answer to that question
just looking at the the um
the the architecture of the kind that's
being presented on screen now. So um if
if there is any um hierarchal or
heterarchical structure
induced by the um the sparse coupling of
any dynamics whether they're
intracellular dynamics or whether
they're the the connector in a brain. Um
then that hierarchal structure just is
defined by a series of nested markoff
blankets. Um and just to keep things
simple, you can imagine, you know, a a
sandwich cake or a layer cake of markoff
blanket after Markoff blanket. Um from
the point of view of any given Markoff
blanket, um what is it seeing and what
who is it talking to? So the Markoff
blanket is just an expression of the
inputs and the outputs. So in this
simplified picture of concentric or
layer cakes or hierarchical subs
hierarchy of mark of blankets then
effectively um one level is basically
seeing the outputs of another level. So
it's basically seeing the active states
of another level and the the active
states of the given level say level I um
now provide the inputs namely the
sensory states of the level uh of the
level below and this becomes
particularly obvious when you think
about predictive coding hierarchies. So
predictive coding hierarchies um you
have this notion of um ascending and
descending messages where the ascending
messages are effectively the free energy
gradients or the prediction errors
usually precision weighted prediction
errors that um ascend from lower levels
of the hierarchy, lower markoff blankets
if you like to the next markoff blanket
which would be the you know the next
level up. um and then they are
reciprocated
inducing the circular causality which
you always require when thinking about
anything embedded in its environment um
by descending predictions. So the actual
messages what is seen and what and what
and what is acted well in this instance
um the
the act we're associating action with um
descending predictions that but usually
those predictions are going to be a
precision to do the selection we were
talking about but more generally we can
think of them as basically um actions on
on the level on the level below. So what
that basically means is that if I'm one
markoff blanket and I have hidden states
within you know um behind me I am
basically trying to make sense of the
prediction errors that are coming from
the markoff blanket below me. And in
making sense of those, I am now acting
on those blankets by um issuing
predictions
that I am now going to be using in order
to evaluate the prediction error. And
then you you know if you actually write
out the requisite variables in a
predictive coding scheme and just look
at the links you can you can quite
easily identify um the implicit markoff
blankets layer after layer after layer.
Do you have more questions on chat or
do you want to ask any or I can get
another one chat?
Yeah. Say
have another question from the um
the figure 4 like uh can you can you
stay there on the figure four?
Uhhuh.
Um like every um CR reference frame has
in and outside um
connection to the executive um or meta
cognitive um screen
but the um thermodynamic um free energy
distribution quer reference frame the
top one has only an input the output is
then uh through valves that um
co-regulate I guess um the qual
reference frame activation.
So yeah, uh I was thinking why is there
only one direction?
Um
and isn't then the theodynamic
um
free energy distribution quantum
reference frame? That's a terrible name
by the way. Um uh isn't this then higher
in the hierarchy than the executive? um
which could be um
answer to the question that um dorsal
attention overrides like the other
something like this.
I'm not sure. Yeah, I think a related
question that I have to that is like if
layers be get another layer
then
what is structurally different about the
inner screen?
Does it imply
similar awarenesses?
Where does the narrative
self-identification
relate to these finite hierarchies
which come to a stop just through the
finitness of things?
But that might be a Chris question
related to this diagram.
I guess sort of just in a closingish
round
from from Adam and Carl, how do you see
this work going forward? What would you
be looking to reduce your uncertainty
with further?
What kinds of uh predictions or
experiments do you feel like came out of
that? Or how did the discussions of the
authors relate to
What takeaways and what research
directions
arise now?
Maybe Adam first.
Well, I never know actually. Um
I'd first like to be surprised um in
terms of um uh just seeing like
independently con like what people come
up with cuz you know I I approach this
from a very different take um than being
like grounded in the formalism. You know
I come from like a systems neuroscience
and cybernetic perspective. Um but and
so like the ways there are differences
are in some ways most interesting to me
but also the points of convergence. But
the um I guess
wondering how far we could go with the
um quasi cartisian interpretations
um like um going not going too far um
but going far enough um wondering um
whether it can bear so like um earlier
Carl mentioned um like mental
transparency but like what different um
aspects of consciousness studies and
phenomenologies can be elucidated by
further developments So something I
posted in the um uh Zoom chat was like
um there's been suggestions of um uh you
know there being potentially a basian
blur problem and interpretations of um
the brain as a generative model that
could produce awareness like why doesn't
um experience seem probabilistic like
why don't we get superp positions why
does it seem so classical and so like um
Andy Clark for instance um you know
discussed this in terms of like the
requirement of consciousness to be like
in terms of its functional role is being
coupled to mental action or policy
selection and um you know that's doesn't
seem incompatible with what's being
proposed here but I wonder like to what
degree um is this inner screen having
classical properties part of what
mediates this um transition um or rather
part of what would explain another way
not necessarily mutually exclusive
because the screen is helping for
precision waiting and mental action and
intentional selection but to what degree
Is this another um uh complimentary or
or separate um solution to the so-called
basian blur problem um to the extent
that it is a problem? Um, one more thing
I guess I would wonder is in terms of
like unpacking quasi cartisian
intuitions is so like in the work with
like Tim like these like two data
structures they have are like a view
network and a pose network that are like
closely coupled for like the state of
the um embodied agent relative to the
world or for the robot. And something I
would wonder is like um this inner
screen to what extent does it have um
like the properties that would
correspond to some of the phenomenology
of space? Like to what degree is it
connected to like visual spatial
awareness? Um but like to what degree
does it um connect to sematospaceial
awareness? Is that subsumed into visual
spatial awareness? Is there only one
modality? Are there multiple spaces?
Like these are I guess um uh questions
I've wondered about in terms of like you
know um what is the relationship between
like what I guess phenomenologists might
sometimes describe like the lived body
and um what we might the folk might call
or what people might call the mind's
eye. So I I have a lot of different
questions and and um um wondering
whether um whether further developments
of this theory could um constrain some
of the many places I have uncertainty.
[Music]
So just to pick up on some of the key
issues that Adam's just uh foregrounded
for us. Um
so the the basian blur I only understand
through Andy Clark's writing and I think
um Adam picked up on a very important
point there that um comes back to what
we're talking about before in terms of
the the differences between intentions
and action. Action is a real variable.
It's not a random variable. You can only
infer a random variable. So that means
that your actual action including your
mental action is not a random variable
and it cannot have a probability
distribution. It just is. So the
manifestation of your mental actions
can't have a a basin blur. Um uh just in
a very simple-minded way
that can also be read in terms of the
act of selection. you can only select
one of many things. Um, and that's why I
quite like it when people use the word
selection or attention selection or
selecting this as opposed to that. Um,
and that the act of selection is in, you
know, selection is a verb. uh and it
does speak to the the um discrete aspect
or the unitary aspect of um manifesting
your intentions
that cannot have a basian blur. So I
think that that's an interesting thing
that inherits from the um the inner
screen. Um the other interesting thing
is that um the inner screen because it
can no longer the innermost screen I
apologies because it can no longer be
subpartitioned
um thereby enabling more and more
abstract explanations for um parts of
the inner screen. The only way that it
can know itself
is by acting on its world. But of
course, its world is just the rest of
the brain for us or the rest of the cell
for for a bacterium,
which means that it can only um know
itself through acting.
And that's quite unique to the inner
screen. Um and what does that mean um in
terms of future research? Well, it means
that there may be some one or more. I'm
not saying there's just one in a screen.
there could be a number of them in a
hetarchical structure. um um but it does
beg the question now what is the
functional anatomy of this inner screen
um from a biological point of view and
that's why I sort of make you know
deliberately um um emphasized the
neurobiology
and the neuropharmacology of this mental
action Alice Mark zones because we know
there has to be connections from the
inner screen to the cells of origin or
the things that do the mental action
which ultimately reduced to um casical
sending neurom modulatory systems. So
we've got a good start in principle for
the neur neurobiology of it. On the
other hand, you might start to um apply
these ideas and the predictions to um
artificial consciousness. So we wanted
to simulate consciousness or perhaps we
were worried about the ethics of AI
alignment. Um can machines suffer? Uh
are they self-aware? And all of these
questions I think rest very much upon
the functional architectures and the
implicit information geometries that you
are um literally in a position to build.
Um and then you're asking questions
about well where would selfawareness
live? Well, it would have to live in
that inner screen um or in that
innermost screen because as every time
you you you move behind these successive
screens, you are um from a technical
point of view compressing your fantasies
about what's causing your sensoria of
sensoria of sensoria. And that
compression ultimately reduces to the
simplest explanation for my sensorium in
that it's me.
So you the which is just another
hypothesis but it's a nice simple
explanation for gathering together all
these different modalities Adam's
talking about sort of visual uh visual
modalities the auditory the intraceptive
um all of these can be jointly explained
by a very simple hypothesis. Oh, I am an
embodied artifact.
More precisely, it's not just I am one
because if there was just one
hypothesis, there would be no hypothesis
to select from. So there would be no
active selection. Um so you would never
know that. But as soon as you have
different different hypotheses about you
in different states of mind or you uh in
different states of being, you can now
act upon your brain and ultimately your
body to contextualize and gather
evidence. Yes, I am in this state of
mind. Uh everything that I'm receiving
from my intraceptive modalities, visual
modalities, auditory modalities tells me
that currently I am scared. you know,
I'm in a dark alley in a city that I do
not know. My my heart is racing. Um I
feel um petrified. The best explanation
for this is that it is me in this
particular state of mind. Um and if I
know I'm in that state of mind, then I
can act by selectively attenuating or
attending to various sources of
information. Um I will probably in this
instance attend acutely to my auditory
modalities less to my visual um but also
attend acutely um or in fact no I will
actually attenuate my attention to um uh
my um bodily states in preparation for
flight and fight. And of course in so
doing I will engage different kinds of
reflexes and generate more evidence that
I am in a state of um panic angst um or
at least arousal and alertness that
would prepare me. So you
to come back to where I started you
would you want to build that into a into
a robot? you might well do if you
believe people like Yosha Bach for
example, you if you want um if you want
to elude the singularity
then he would argue you really need to
make uh artifacts as conscious and
empathetic as we are. Um, so you might
have to move in in that sort of biometic
direction in order to guarantee um true
AI alignment right right across the
board.
A great place to take it and leave it
for now. So thank you to the authors for
the very provocative paper and for
joining this discussion and to Koya for
precipitating it and giving a lot of
thought to it as well. So best of luck
till the next screen stream.
Thanks.
Bye.